MARK KAMUDA

phone: 847-917-0302 \(\phi\) email: kamuda1@illinois.edu \(\phi\) web: http://kamuda1.github.io

SUMMARY

Machine learning research engineer with 4 years of experience leveraging simulated data and deep learning algorithms to solve real-world signal classification and regression problems. Looking to transfer my deep learning and research skills to develop reliable solutions to complex problems.

SKILLS

Python, TensorFlow, Keras, scikit-learn, Pandas, Numpy, Jupyter Notebooks, MATLAB, Amazon Web Service, Git/GitHub, Monte Carlo simulation, statistical modeling, sampling techniques, digital signal processing, Linux, Bash

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Artificial Neural Network for Spectral Analysis (link)

- Developed and prototyped an open source Python package for deep learning with noisy spectroscopic data
- Researched and evaluated dense, convolution, and autoencoder neural networks for problems in nuclear security
- Performed feature engineering using autoencoders
- Applied software development best practices such as unit testing, version control, and automated documentation
- Designed, built, and simulated custom datasets for training and experiments

A Comparison of Machine Learning Methods for Automated Gamma-Ray Spectroscopy

- Compared convolution and dense neural networks for multiclass spectroscopic signal classification
- Studied both algorithms' generalization performance on simulated data
- Published results in Nuclear Instruments and Methods in Physics Research Section A

Automated Isotope Identification Algorithm Using Artificial Neural Networks

- Employed a logarithmic regression neural network for multiclass multilabel signal regression
- Published results in IEEE Transactions on Nuclear Science

EDUCATION

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, Illinois

Doctorate, Nuclear Engineering Masters, Nuclear Engineering Bachelors, Nuclear Engineering Aug 2017 - Oct 2019 (expected) May 2014 - August 2017 August 2010 - May 2014

WORK EXPERIENCE

Guest Scientist, Los Alamos National Laboratory

June 2015 - Aug 2015

- Performed data mining and statistical analysis on legacy data to improve nuclear forensics capabilities
- Presented results in a Los Alamos National Laboratory internal report

Guest Scientist, Brookhaven National Laboratory

May 2013 - Aug 2013

- Participated in the Department of Energys Science Undergraduate Laboratory Internship
- Simulated and evaluated a novel collimator design for a compact medical scanner
- Applied a maximum likelihood expectation maximization algorithm to reconstruct and localize tumors
- Presented results in a poster and published paper

LEADERSHIP

The Hacker Within-Illinois, President

Aug 2018 - May 2019

- Effectively managed a software skill-sharing club of over 25 members
- Leveraged communication skills to sustain membership by encouraging participation and planning creative topics
- Developed and delivered multiple technical presentations and tutorials

Engineering Outreach Society, President

Aug 2013 - May 2014

- Headed an outreach organization of over 50 students with an executive board of five people
- Coordinated weekly science projects with a team of ten elementary school teachers

PUBLICATIONS

- E. J. Hague, M. Kamuda, W. P. Ford, E. T. Moore, and J. Turk. "A comparison of adaptive and template matching techniques for radio-isotope identification." SPIE Proceedings.
- M. Kamuda and C.J. Sullivan. "An Automated Isotope Identification and Quantification Algorithm for Isotope Mixtures in Low-Resolution Gamma-ray Spectra." Radiation Physics and Chemistry.

 2019
- M. Kamuda, J. Zhao, K. Huff. "A Comparison of Machine Learning Methods for Automated Gamma-Ray Spectroscopy." Nuclear Instruments and Methods in Physics Research Section A.

 2018
- M. Kamuda, J. Stinnett, and C.J. Sullivan. "Automated Isotope Identification Algorithm Using Artificial Neural Networks." IEEE Transactions on Nuclear Science.
- J. Mattingly, J. Hutchinson, C. Sullivan, J. Stinnett, M. Kamuda, M. Alamaniotis, B. Simms, J. Mueller, J. Newby, J. Linkous, S. Pozzi, K. Polack, M. Hamel, Z. He, D. Goodman, and M. Streicher. "CNEC and CVT Subcritical Experiments with Category I Special Nuclear Material at the Nevada National Security Site Device Assembly Facility." Institute of Nuclear Materials Management Conference Record.

 2016
- M. Kamuda et al. "Modeling Of A Slanted-hole Collimator In A Compact Endo-cavity Gamma Camera." SPIE Proceedings.

 2013

SELECTED PRESENTATIONS

- M. Kamuda. "Preventing Disaster: Identifying Nuclear Weapons with Neural Networks." Poster presented at SciPy 2019, Autin, Texas.
- M. Kamuda. "A Machine Learning Approach To Identifying Shielded Radioisotopes In Gamma-ray Spectra." Poster presented at the Consortium For Verification Technology Workshop, Ann Arbor, Michigan. 2018
- M. Kamuda. "Uranium Enrichment Measurements Using an Artificial Neural Network." Podium presentation given at the Consortium for Verification Technology Workshop, Ann Arbor, Michigan.

 2017
- M. Kamuda and C.J. Sullivan. "An Automated Isotope Identification and Quantification Algorithm for Isotope Mixtures in Low-Resolution Gamma-ray Spectra." Podium presentation given at the 10th International Topical Meeting on Industrial Radiation and Radioisotope Measurement Applications, Chicago, Illinois.

 2017
- M. Kamuda, J. Stinnett, C.J. Sullivan. "Peak Quantification with Neural Networks for Low-Resolution NaI Spectra." Poster presented at the IEEE Nuclear Science Symposium, Medical Imaging Conference and Room-Temperature Semiconductor Detector Workshop (NSS/MIC/RTSD), Strasbourg, France.
- M. Kamuda and C.J. Sullivan. "An Automated Isotope Identification and Quantification Algorithm for Isotope Mixtures in Low-Resolution Gamma-ray Spectra." Poster presented at the Symposium on Radiation Measurements and Applications, Berkeley, California.
- M. Kamuda, M.M. Watson, and C.J. Sullivan. "Information Barriers based on Enhanced Automated Isotope Identification." Poster presented at the University and Industry Technical Interchange Program and Technical Review Meeting, Ann Arbor, Michigan.
 2015

GUIDED DISCUSSIONS

- M. Kamuda. "Posting to GitHub and Reviewing Legacy Code." The Hacker Within, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign2019
- M. Kamuda. "Data Visualization." The Hacker Within, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign 2018
- M. Kamuda and J. Drobny. "Intro to Python & Python Tips." The Hacker Within, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign 2018
- M. Kamuda and J. Wilson. "Data Mining and Machine Learning." The Hacker Within, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign 2018
- M. Kamuda. "Natural Language Processing." The Hacker Within, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign 2017
- M. Kamuda. "Introduction to TensorFlow." The Hacker Within, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign 2017